<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The cures of the diseased, in remote regions Preventing mortalitie, incident in forraine attempts, of the English nation.</title>
            <author>Wateson, George, fl. 1598-1607.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1598</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 21 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14806</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25106A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113241</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848478</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848478</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13574</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14806)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13574)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1674:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The cures of the diseased, in remote regions Preventing mortalitie, incident in forraine attempts, of the English nation.</title>
                  <author>Wateson, George, fl. 1598-1607.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[28] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By F[elix] K[ingston], for H[umfrey] L[ownes],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1598.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: George Wateson.</note>
                  <note>Printer's and publisher's names from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D⁴ (-A1,D4).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13574:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CVRES OF the Diſeaſed, in remote <hi>Regions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>PREVENTING MORTALI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi> incident in Forraine Attempts, of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation.</p>
            <q xml:lang="spa">
               <l>La honra mas vale,</l>
               <l>merecerla que tenerla.</l>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <q>BY WISDOME PEACE BY PEACE PLENTY</q>
               <figDesc>printer's device of F. Kingston: clasped hands emerging from clouds holding a caduceus and two cornucopias</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>At London</hi> Printed by <hi>F.K.</hi> for <hi>H. L.</hi> 1598.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:13574:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13574:2"/>
            <head>TO THE QVEENES MOST EXCELLENT MAIESTIE.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Acred Soueraigne,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>in my iniust impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment in <hi>Spayne,</hi> it pleaſed God to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict me with the <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bardilla</hi> Peſtilence: whereof being in cure, by an eſpeciall Phiſition of that King, J obſerued his methode for the ſame, and ſuch other Diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, as haue periſhed your Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties people in the <hi>Southerne</hi> parts. Which Remedies haue ſince, by my direction, taken the like good effects.
<pb facs="tcp:13574:3"/>And of perfect zeale to your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties ſeruice, and Countries weale, J therewith acquaint your Highnes ſubiects. Jnuocating God to preſerue your Maiestie, enable them in your ſeruices, protect your King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, and ſuppreſse your Enemies.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Maiesties loyall Subiect <hi>George Wateſon.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:13574:3"/>
            <head>The Writers intent.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>MAn that is borne, not for himſelfe is borne,</l>
               <l>But for his Prince, his Countrie, and his friends.</l>
               <l>To helpe the ſicke, diſtreſſed, and forlorne,</l>
               <l>Are workes of mercie, men to men extends.</l>
               <l>Who hath the power, and meanes, and will not cheriſh,</l>
               <l>Shall with the hider of his Tallent periſh.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Tranſgreſsion firſt did ſinne in man beget,</l>
               <l>Sinne, ſicknes, death, and miſchiefes many more:</l>
               <l>For as mens mindes on wickedneſs were ſet,</l>
               <l>So plagues increaſt, which were not knowne before.</l>
               <l>But God, whoſe mercie, iuſtice doth exceed,</l>
               <l>Sends helps for hurts, and ſalues for ſores at need.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poetical_exposition_of_books_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:13574:4"/>
            <head>The Bookes Content.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>The burning Feuer, calde the <hi>Calenture,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The aking <hi>Tabardilla</hi> pestilent,</l>
               <l>Th' <hi>Eſpinlas</hi> prickings, which men do endure,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cameras de Sangre,</hi> Fluxes violent,</l>
               <l>Th' <hi>Erizipila,</hi> ſwelling the Pacient,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Tin<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>oſo,</hi> which we the <hi>Scuruey</hi> call,</l>
               <l>Are truly here deſcrib'd, and cured all.</l>
            </lg>
            <epigraph>
               <q xml:lang="spa">
                  <l>Si Dios no es adorado,</l>
                  <l>nunca ſeras bien curado.</l>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="medical_text">
            <pb facs="tcp:13574:4"/>
            <head>The Cures of the Diſeaſed, in remote Regions.</head>
            <div type="disease">
               <head>THE CALENT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RE.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He <hi>Calenture</hi> (or bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Feuer) called by the <hi>Spaniards, La Calen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura,</hi> is the moſt vſuall Diſeaſe, happening to our Nation in intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Climats, by inflammation of blood, and often proceeding of immoderate drinking of wine, and eating of pleaſant Fruits, which are ſuch nouriſhers thereof, as they preuent the conuenient meanes, that are vſed in curing the ſame.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:13574:5"/>
                  <head>To know the <hi>Calenture.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THe <hi>Calenture</hi> at the firſt apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on afflicts the Pacient with great paine in the head, and heate in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die; which is continuall or increaſing, and doth not diminiſh and augment as other Feuers doo: and is an introducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the <hi>Tabardilla,</hi> or Peſtilence; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of next is intreated: but then the bodie will ſeeme very yellow.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>To cure the <hi>Calenture.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>SO ſoone as the Pacient is perceiued to be poſſeſt of the <hi>Calenture;</hi> except the Chirurgion defer it for danger of the Signe (I haue ſeene the time of the day not reſpected) to open the <hi>Median veine</hi> of the right arme, and take ſuch quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie of blood, as agreeth to the abilitie of the bodie, which not aſſwaging the heate, by the next day; to open the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:13574:5"/>Veine in the left arme, and take ſo much more blood at his like diſcretion. And the bodie being Coſtiue (for ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly the Pacients are) to giue him ſome meete Purgation; and not to permit him to drinke other then water coolde, wherein Barley &amp; Anniſeedes haue been ſodden with bruſed Licorice. And if with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in foure daies the partie doo not amend, or being recouered doo take it againe; then open the <hi>Sephalica veine,</hi> in one or both hands, bathing them in warme water, vntill there comes ſo much more blood as cauſe requires. And not to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the Pacient to drinke, ſeuen dayes af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he is perfectlie recouered, any other drinke, then ſuch water as herein is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="disease">
               <head>THE TABARDILLA.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Diſeaſe called by the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards, La Tabardilla,</hi> and by the <hi>Mexicans, Cocalista,</hi> is named by other <hi>Jndians, Taberdet:</hi> and is ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding
<pb facs="tcp:13574:6"/>Peſtilent and infectious, as by the ſame, whole Kingdomes in both the <hi>Jndias</hi> haue been depopulated: which ſeemeth to inſue of the ignorance of the ſauage people, to miniſter redreſſe to themſelues. For the <hi>Spaniards</hi> and <hi>Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gals</hi> there inhabiting, and in their natiue Countries, where it is alſo contagious, before they had this knowledge, did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundantlie die thereof. But now by ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying the meanes here deſcribed, they are recouered of the ſame.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>To know the <hi>Tabardilla.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THe <hi>Tabardilla</hi> firſt aſſaults the Paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent very veheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly, with pain in the head and backe: and the bodie ſeeming yellow, is ſome ſigne thereof, and within 24. howres it is ſo torturous, that he that is poſſeſt therof, cannot ſleep or reſt, tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning himſelfe on either ſide, backe and bellie; burning in his backe moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamely. And when it growes to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection,
<pb facs="tcp:13574:6"/>there will appeare red and blew ſpots vpon the Pacients breſt and wriſts. And ſuch perſons as haue not preſently applyed vnto them, meanes requiſite to preuent it, will be by the incomparable torment thereof, depriued of their wits. And multitudes haue deſparingly ſlaine and drowned themſelues, that by loſſe of their liues, they might finiſh their ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtriall paine.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>To cure the <hi>Tabardilla.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>WHen the <hi>Tabardilla</hi> is perceiued to afflict the Pacient, permit him not to lie very warme, nor vpon Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers (for of what qualitie ſoeuer he is in <hi>Spayne,</hi> hauing this ſicknes, he is layd vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Wheate ſtraw:) Then immediatly o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen the <hi>Median veine,</hi> firſt in one arme, and the next day in the other, taking a good quantitie of blood: And let him haue water colde, wherein Barley and Anniſeedes haue been ſodden, without
<pb facs="tcp:13574:7"/>Licorice (for I haue heard the opinion of good Phiſitions of <hi>Spayne,</hi> that Licorice is hurtfull vnto them) ſo much as he will deſire, which will be euery moment: but no other drinke, nor any rawfruits: and ſo ſoone as the ſpots appeare, giue him ſome Cordiall potion: and laying him vpon his bellie, ſet ſixe <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>entoſes</hi> together in his backe, betweene and beneath the ſhoulders. And ſcarifying them, draw out (if it bee a bodie of ſtrong conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) 18. ounces of blood. After which, and that he hath ſlept, he will feele eaſe within 24. houres, and finde ſuch altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in himſelfe, as he will thinke that he is deliuered of a moſt ſtrange torment. Then giuing him nouriſhing meats mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deratly (for he will deſire to eate much) the fourth day giue him ſome co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient Purgation. And if in the meane while he is Coſtiue, prouoke him euery day by Cliſters: and admoniſh him to forbeare fifteene daies all other drinke, then that is ordained. And to bee carefull of his
<pb facs="tcp:13574:7"/>diet: for if this <hi>Tabardilla,</hi> which we call here in <hi>England,</hi> Gods Tokens, come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine vnto the Pacient, he can hardly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape it. And it is no leſſe infectious, then the vſuall Engliſh Plague.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="disease">
               <head>THE ESPINLAS.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He <hi>Eſpinlas</hi> is a very ſtrange ſicknes, and vſuall in thoſe parts, to ſuch as take cold in their breaſts, after great heat or trauell. And moſt times it comes to thoſe that lye with their breaſts vpon the ground (eſpecially) in the night.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>To know the <hi>Eſpinlas.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THe partie hauing the <hi>Eſpinlas,</hi> will be giddie in the head, and haue pain and pricking at his breaſt, as with many thornes: wherefore I thinke it is ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led of <hi>Spina</hi> and <hi>Eſpina,</hi> the Latine and Spaniſh words for a Thorne. And there
<pb facs="tcp:13574:8"/>will be vpon <hi>Hueſso radio,</hi> or <hi>Focell,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the vpper bone of his arme, a hand breadth aboue the wriſt, a little kernell, by which it is certainly knowne. And he that hath this Diſeaſe, will not haue ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite to meate or drinke; nor cannot digeſt meate, although he bee procured to take it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>To cure the <hi>Eſpinlas.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THe <hi>Eſpinlas,</hi> appearing by the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſignes: Take Oliue oyle pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently, and therewith chafe the kernell vpon the Pacients arme, vſing ſo to doe twiſe euery day, vntill it bee diſſolued: and laying Oyle likewiſe vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his breaſt, ſtroke it vpwarde ſomewhat hard with the hand: then ſpread fine Flaxe vpon it and the kernell, making it faſt with a rowler: and within two or three dayes, the diſeaſed thereof will be recouered. Whereas els it is very dangerous to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priue them of life.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="disease">
               <pb facs="tcp:13574:8"/>
               <head>LAS CAMERAS, OR Cameras de Sangre.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HAT is Laxatiuenes, or Bloodie Fluxe, which in thoſe parts proceedes of diuers cauſes. As by ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Grapes, Orringes, Limonds, Mellons, Plantans, and eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a great Fruit that growes in the <hi>VVeſt Jndia,</hi> called <hi>Pina,</hi> like a Pine-apple, but bigger then foure of the greateſt that I haue ſeene; which the <hi>Spanyards</hi> doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute to be the moſt delicate Fruit that is there, and many other Fruites. Alſo by ſudden colde, or ſitting (being very hot) vpon a colde ſtone, or, being hot, by drinking Water abundantly. And alſo eating of Butter, Oyle, and Fiſh, is ſo hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to the parties that haue it, that they muſt refraine to eate thereof: and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſouer els, that defiles the entrailes, with any ſlimie ſubſtance.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:13574:9"/>
                  <head>To cure <hi>Las Cameras,</hi> or <hi>Cameras de Sangre,</hi> which is the <hi>Bloodie Flux.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>VVIth the more expedition, that medicine is miniſtred to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſed of <hi>Cameras de Sangre, Laxatiuenes,</hi> or <hi>Bloodie Flux,</hi> there is the more poſsibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie it ſhould preuaile. And detracting it, the Pacients often die ſuddenly, without feeling much griefe. For ſpeedie and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured remedie thereof, the Pacients bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die muſt bee clenſed of the ſlimines, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendered in the paſſages of the nutri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, before anie ſuſtinance can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine in his bodie. And for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, giue to purge him in the morning, halfe a pint of white Wine coold, wherin ½. ounce of Rubarb hath been ſodden, being ſmall cut; putting in ſome Suger Candie to ſweeten it. And immediatly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he hath ſo purged, keepe at his nauell Roſemarie ſodden in ſtrong Vineger, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied
<pb facs="tcp:13574:9"/>in the morning and euening verie hot, vntill it be ſtayed: giuing him often Quinces bruſed and rowled in Marme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let like Pils, which hee ſhould ſwallowe whole, and none of the Fruits, or meates before recited, nor any more white wine, but red wine of any ſort. And if it be on Land, the liuers of Goates (eſpeciallie) Sheepe, or Bullocks roſted: not willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly permitting the Pacient to eate any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meate. And if at Sea, Rice only ſod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in water, rather then any thing elſe vſuall there, vntill the infirmitie is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly aſſwaged.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="disease">
               <head>THE ERIZIPILA.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He <hi>Erizipila</hi> is a Diſeaſe very much raigning in thoſe Countries, the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther proceeding of the vnholeſome aires and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours, that hot Climates doo yeelde, whereof many people doo periſh. And
<pb facs="tcp:13574:10"/>it is found incurable, except it be preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Medicines, preſently miniſtred to the Pacients vexed therewith.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>To know the <hi>Erizipila.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>HE that hath the <hi>Erizipila,</hi> will bee ſwolne in the face, or ſome part of him, and it will be of yellow colour mixt with red. And when it is thruſt with the finger, there will remaine a ſigne or dint of the ſame: and then by degrees it will fill againe to the former proportion. And it ſpeedily infecteth the inwarde parts, becauſe ſuch ſwellings comes ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to perfection in hot places, then in temperate Countries. And therefore the diſeaſed thereof, muſt bee immediatlie prouided of remedie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>To cure the <hi>Erizipila.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>SOme ſauage people haue firſt found perfectly to cure this <hi>Erizipila,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
<pb facs="tcp:13574:10"/>it is the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> name of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladie; by bruſing ſo much <hi>Tobaco,</hi> as will yeeld foure ſpoonfuls of iuyce, and to drinke it preſently after they are infected therewith. And to launce the places ſwolne; thereunto putting <hi>Caſada</hi> wet, and made in paſte. Continuing in colde places and ſhadie, neere Riuers: and not to trauell or labour, vntill they are reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered. But the <hi>Spanyards</hi> in <hi>Jndia,</hi> reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer themſelues by taking the ſame iuyce of <hi>Tobaco,</hi> and ſetting ſo many <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>entoſes</hi> vpon the ſwolne places, as they can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, ſcarrifying them, and drawing out the corrupted Humour ſo congealed. And doing the like in two or three other parts of the bodie, where the Diſeaſe doth not appeare.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The iuice of</hi> Tobaco, <hi>is very excellent to expell Poyſon, and is the ordinarie remedie vſed by the</hi> Indians, <hi>and many other ſauage people, when they are poyſoned, and bit with Scorpions, or other venemous creatures. But
<pb facs="tcp:13574:11"/>they preſently make ſome kinde of inciſion, where they are bit or ſtung, and waſh it with the iuyce of</hi> Tobaco: <hi>then applying the ſame bruſed thereunto, two or three dayes, they heale it vp with dried</hi> Tobaco.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="disease">
               <head>THE TINOSO.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He <hi>Tin<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>oſo,</hi> or <hi>Sceruey</hi> is an infecting Diſeaſe, ſufficientlie knowne vnto Seafaring men: who by putrified meates, and corrupted drinkes, eating Bisket flowrie, or foule cruſted, wearing wet apparell (eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſleeping in it) and ſlothfull demea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, or by groſſe humours contained in their bodies, obtaine the ſame.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>To know the <hi>Scuruey.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>ALthough moſt Chirurgions, and chiefly thoſe that frequent the Sea, doo vnderſtand how to diſcerne when their Pacients haue the <hi>Scuruey;</hi> becauſe
<pb facs="tcp:13574:11"/>it is ſo ordinary at Sea, as it hath been ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ſeene, any Ship or Pinnice, to bee foure moneths vpon any Voyage, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny part of the world, not ariuing where they haue been ſupplied and relieued with the benefits of the Land: but ſome of the Companie haue had this Diſeaſe. Yet it is not impertinent here to inſert the ſignes thereof: the rather, becauſe I haue known ſome ſo deſtitute of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, to diſcerne and cure the ſame, as the loſſe of men loſt thereby, hath diuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted determined purpoſes to proceed on Voyages: and others to periſh, when they returned out of hot Regions into cold Climates, where they haue had the lineaments of their bodies, that with heate are nimble and tractable to euerie motion of the ſpirits, dulled and benum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with colde: which is a token that this diſeaſe is engendring in their ioints: and ſooneſt appeares by ſwelling of their anckles and knees, and blacknes of their gummes, or looſenes of their teeth,
<pb facs="tcp:13574:12"/>which will ſometimes come forth, when there is not redreſſe miniſtred in ſeaſon.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Preſeruatines againſt <hi>the Scuruey.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>TO preſerue men from the <hi>Scuruie,</hi> there muſt be care to prepare thoſe things before rehearſed, well conditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: the badnes whereof doth partlie breede the inconuenience. And men themſelues muſt haue a diſcreet ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to auoid their owne ruine, by vſing exerciſe of their bodies. And ſuch as are exempted from being commanded to doo labour, to hang by the armes twiſe or thrice euery day. And not to haue ſcarcitie of drinke in hot Climates: and comming into the cold, to be daily relie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with <hi>Aqua vitae,</hi> or wine. Alſo it is a certaine and aſſured medicine againſt this Diſeaſe, to haue ſuch quantitie of Beere brewed with Graynes and Long pepper, as in the morning twiſe euerie
<pb facs="tcp:13574:12"/>week there may be giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a good draught to a man, proportioning three quarters of a pound of Graines, and three quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of a pound of Pepper to a hogſhead of Beere. But white Wine or Syder, boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and brewed with Graynes and Long pepper, in like quantitie, is very ſingular good. And it is not fit to ſuffer the gums to abound with fleſh: and therfore ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times let them bleede, and cleere them with ſtrong Vineger.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>To cure the <hi>Scuruey.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THe partie that hath the <hi>Scuruey</hi> ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in his mouth, muſt haue the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted and black fleſh take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away, waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his mouth with ſtrong Vineger, wherein Graines and Long pepper haue been infuſed and brewed: and giue him the drinke daily that is before preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed. And aſwell ſuch as haue it in their mouthes, as thoſe that are ſwolne in their limmes, muſt haue ſome meete Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:13574:13"/>preſently. But thoſe ſo ſwolne or ſtiffe (for ſo ſome will bee without ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling) to ſcarifie the parts infected, and to applie thereunto a <hi>Pultis</hi> or <hi>Cataplaſme</hi> of Barley meale, more hot then the Paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent will willingly ſuffer it. So doing eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie morning, permit him not to reſt two houres after, although hee being num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med or faint, be ſupported to walke: and not to ſuffer him to eate any ſalt meates, if other may be had.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My ſelfe hauing</hi> 80. <hi>men,</hi> 800. <hi>leagues forth of</hi> England, <hi>ſicke of the</hi> Scuruey, <hi>J cauſed this meanes of ſcarifying to be vſed, and to the places ſcarified, Pulteſes (being destitute of the helpes mentioned) to bee ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied of Bisket, beaten in a morter, and ſod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in water: which with the comfort of ſome freſh meates (obtained) recouered them all, except one perſon, and they arriued in</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>perfectly ſound.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <pb facs="tcp:13574:13"/>
               <head>Concluſion.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>Let no man boaſt of beautie, ſtrength, or youth:</l>
                  <l>For like to flowres we bud, we ſpread, we fade:</l>
                  <l>Nothing is certaine, but the certaine truth,</l>
                  <l>To day a man, to morrow but a ſhade.</l>
                  <l>His laſt apparell, cut out with a ſpade,</l>
                  <l>Of Natures courſeſt ſtuffe (I meane) her molde,</l>
                  <l>Muſt ſhrowd the corps, that liuing ſhone in golde.</l>
               </lg>
               <epigraph>
                  <q xml:lang="spa">
                     <l>Quando tengas, mas fortuna,</l>
                     <l>mira que es, como la Luna.</l>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:13574:14"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE cauſe that induceth mee, publiquelie to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the Cures of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes of ſuch conſequence, as euery iudiciall conceite may perceiue, to haue been the onely preiudice to our Nation, in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peditions of our time to the Southerne parts: from whence in this and former ages, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> haue returned with renowmed <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ictorie; yet exceedinglie opprest with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame and penurious ſickneſſe, that hath much more preuented the proceeding and performing of their pretentions, than the power of Enemies: is not that J purpoſe, practitioner-like in Phiſick or Chirurgerie, to aſsume vnto me anie knowledge in thoſe Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences and Faculties: but to poſſeſſe all men
<pb facs="tcp:13574:14"/>of remedie for ſuch infirmities, as in my owne experience, haue infinitelie impaired <hi>Engliſh</hi> Forces in intemperate Clymates. VVhich J publiſh, for the good of thoſe, whom cauſe may compell to haue vſe thereof, and would be ſo cenſured of all.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:13574:15"/>
            <p>Imprinted at Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don by <hi>Felix Kingſton, for</hi> Humfrey Lownes. 1598.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:13574:15"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
